Boker tov בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's daf דף daf is kuf
yud chet ק"יח, kuf yud chet, 118. We pick up at the
bottom of kuf yud zayin amud bet ק"יז עמוד ב'. kuf yud
zayin amud bet. V'chosem
b'geula וחותם בגאולה, v'chosem b'geula, so we're actually a good deal behind
the two dots, not the bottom, about the top third of kuf
yud zayin amud bet ק"יז עמוד ב', kuf yud zayin amud bet,
about six lines before the lines get wide. V'chosem b'geula וחותם בגאולה,
v'chosem b'geula, so now the issue in the Mishnah משנה mishnah that
when you get to the end of the Maggid מגיד, maggid, you
end with the beracha ברכה beracha of Geula גאולה. geula. According to
Rabbi Tarfon, it's just Asher G'alanu אשר גאלנו, asher g'alanu, and Rabbi
Akiva adds the Keen Hashem Elokeinu Yigeinu L'moadim Acherim כן ה' אלהינו
יגיענו למועדים אחרים ken Hashem elokeinu yagi'enu l'mo'adim acherim etcetera, the tefillah
תפילה tefillah for the future, and then with a chatima חתימה chatima
at the end as well. So Amar Rava אמר רבא, amar rava,
so now the Gemara גמרא gemara is going to get into a
discussion about this question, not the debate between Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi
Tarfon, but the question about Ga'al Yisrael גאל ישראל ga'al yisrael in
the past or Go'el Yisrael גואל ישראל go'el yisrael in the future.
Present.
Right, right, thank you, present. Amar Rava אמר רבא, amar rava, I
mean you'll see why I said that because it says sense of
bakasha בקשה, bakasha, but you are correct, it's the present. Amar Rava
אמר רבא, amar rava, Krias Shema v'Hallel קריאת שמע והלל, krias shema
v'hallel, the beracha ברכה beracha that ends Krias Shema קריאת שמע krias
shema right before Shemoneh Esrei שמונה עשרה shemoneh esrei and in Hallel
הלל, hallel, Ga'al Yisrael
גאל ישראל. ga'al yisrael. You know, Hallel הלל hallel does not mean
the normal Hallel הלל, hallel, it means the Hallel הלל hallel of
Erev Pesach ערב פסח, erev pesach, means the end of the Haggadah
הגדה haggadah we say two prakim פרקים prakim of Hallel הלל hallel
as we've been saying. You begin the Hallel הלל, hallel, so it's
interesting they call it Hallel הלל. hallel. I would call it the
beracha ברכה beracha at the end of the Haggadah הגדה, haggadah, but
okay. Anyway, that's the beracha ברכה, beracha, so the beracha ברכה beracha
at the end of the Haggadah הגדה haggadah and Krias Shema קריאת
שמע, krias shema, Ga'al Yisrael גאל ישראל ga'al yisrael in the past.
It's referring to the Geula גאולה geula from Mitzrayim מצרים. mitzrayim. The
tzalusa צלותא tzalusa of the Shemoneh Esrei שמונה עשרה, shemoneh esrei, Go'el
Yisrael גואל ישראל. go'el yisrael. Right, all of the language in the
Shemoneh Esrei שמונה עשרה shemoneh esrei are present. You could also say
they're either present verbs or they're descriptors. I mean, some have actually
claimed that in Hebrew עברית ivrit there's no such thing as the
present. Because every present, like if you say Ani Shomer אני שומר,
ani shomer, does it mean I am a guardian or does it
mean I am watching? Right, and so all of the sort of
present tense are also sort of are also descriptors.
So you say Baruch Atah Hashem ברוך אתה ה', baruch atah Hashem,
participle. Participial? Participial. Isn't participle running?
No, participle can function as a noun or as a verb. It's
a verb form that functions either as a noun or as a
verb.
Okay, I thought I am watching, I thought watching is a participle
because it's like as it's different in Hebrew עברית ivrit because Hebrew
עברית, ivrit, I am a watcher and I am watching are the
same word. Yes. Right. So anyway, so when you say Baruch Atah
Hashem Rofei Cholei Amo Yisrael ברוך אתה ה' רופא חולי עמו ישראל,
baruch atah Hashem rofei cholei amo yisrael, I mean normally when I
say that, I'm thinking God you are capital H, the healer of
the sick of Israel, but you could also think of it as
one who ongoing heals, you know, and in an active way. But
ultimately that is because it's not about something past, it's about your
current relationship to God and the element of bakasha בקשה, bakasha, something
that you are looking towards for God for, you know, the present
and the future. So therefore it's describing your current way of describing
God and of God's activities and therefore it's in the present because
of that element of bakasha בקשה. bakasha.
You mean Rainu Avinu Natrihu Elokeinu ראה נא בענינו r'eh na v'onyenu
beforehand?
No, no, that's Krias Shema קריאת שמע. krias shema. The beracha ברכה
beracha of Ga'al Yisrael גאל ישראל ga'al yisrael that precedes Shemoneh Esrei
שמונה עשרה shemoneh esrei is Krias Shema קריאת שמע. krias shema. The
beracha ברכה beracha in Shemoneh Esrei שמונה עשרה shemoneh esrei is Go'el
Yisrael גואל ישראל go'el yisrael as are all the berachos ברכות berachos
in Shemoneh Esrei שמונה עשרה. shemoneh esrei. Mai ta'ama d'rachamei ni'hu מאי
טעמא דרחמי נינהו mai ta'ama d'rachamei ni'hu because it's rachamei רחמי. rachamei.
Rachamei רחמי rachamei means bakasha בקשה. bakasha. Okay, it could mean the
request for rachamim רחמים, rachamim, but rachamei רחמי rachamei is a technical
term the Gemara גמרא gemara uses in discussing Shemoneh Esrei שמונה עשרה,
shemoneh esrei, which means the bakasha בקשה bakasha element, the sense of
requesting. And therefore you are talking about the sort of present
and a sense of present and future. Amar Rabbi Zeira אמר רבי
זירא, amar rabbi zeira, d'Kiddusha דקידושא, d'kiddusha, the beracha ברכה beracha you
make in Kiddush קידוש kiddush is
Asher Kideshanu B'mitzvosav V'tzivanu אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו. asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu.
Okay, actually not V'tzivanu וצונו, v'tzivanu, they take out V'tzivanu וצונו, v'tzivanu,
right? Asher Kideshanu B'mitzvosav אשר קדשנו במצותיו, asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav, right, what's
the beracha ברכה beracha we say in Kiddush קידוש? kiddush? Baruch Atah
Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam Asher Kideshanu B'mitzvosav
V'ratza Vanu ברוך
אתה ה' אלהינו מלך העולם אשר קדשנו במצותיו ורצה בנו. baruch atah
Hashem elokeinu melech ha'olam asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav v'ratza vanu. Right, so not
V'tzivanu וצונו. v'tzivanu. Okay, you have sanctified us in your mitzvos מצות.
mitzvos. D'tzalusa דצלותא, d'tzalusa, and what we say in Shemoneh Esrei שמונה
עשרה shemoneh esrei is Kadshenu B'mitzvossecha קדשנו במצותיך. kadshenu b'mitzvossecha. So again
the difference: Asher Kideshanu B'mitzvosav אשר קדשנו במצותיו, asher kideshanu b'mitzvosav, you
have in the past sanctified us, V'ratza Vanu ורצה בנו, v'ratza vanu,
right, by Shabbos שבת, shabbos, as opposed to Shemoneh Esrei שמונה עשרה
shemoneh esrei where it's Kadshenu קדשנו, kadshenu, it's a bakasha בקשה, bakasha,
please God sanctify us b'mitzvossecha במצותיך. b'mitzvossecha. Mai ta'ama d'rachamei ni'hu מאי
טעמא דרחמי נינהו, mai ta'ama d'rachamei ni'hu, because of the aspect of
bakasha בקשה. bakasha. Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov אמר רב אחא בר
יעקב, amar rav acha bar yaakov, v'tzarich she'yazkir yetzias mitzrayim b'kiddush hayom
וצריך שיזכיר יציאת מצרים בקידוש היום. v'tzarich she'yazkir yetzias mitzrayim b'kiddush hayom.
You have to mention Yetzias Mitzrayim יציאת מצרים yetzias mitzrayim in Kiddush
קידוש kiddush because you could have said Kiddush קידוש kiddush is about
Ma'aseh Bereishis מעשה בראשית. ma'aseh bereishis. Well, so we're starting with Shabbos
שבת. shabbos. We'll talk about others in a minute. It's about Ma'aseh
Bereishis מעשה בראשית. ma'aseh bereishis. So since when is it about Yetzias
Mitzrayim יציאת מצרים? yetzias mitzrayim? Now of course there are two Luchos
לוחות, luchos, right, in the Aseres Hadibros עשרת הדברות, aseres hadibros, whether
the reference is to
Shabbos
שבת shabbos of Bereishis בראשית. bereishis. has to
be part of the קידוש Kiddush, *Kiddush*. קידוש Kiddush, בערב שבת Shabbos
*Kiddush b'Erev Shabbos*, right? Because he doesn't mean קידוש Kiddush. שבת Shabbos
*Kiddush Shabbos* morning? No, no,
no, the קידוש Kiddush, *Kiddush* is when you say Friday night. Now
כתיב הכא *Ketiv hacha* למען תזכור את יום צאתך מארץ מצרים Mitzrayim,
כל ימי חייך *Lema'an tizkor et yom tzetcha me'eretz mitzrayim kol yemei
chayecha* וכתיב התם *Uchetiv hatam* זכור את יום השבת לקדשו *Zachor et
yom hashabbat lekadesho*. Now again interesting, that is fascinating, because that is
not what I would have said. I would have said that there
are places where the תורה Torah. *Torah* connects the significance of שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* to יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim, *Yetziat Mitzrayim*. וזכרת כי עבד
היית בארץ מצרים Mitzrayim. *Vezacharta ki eved hayita b'Eretz Mitzrayim*. Right? He
connects it somehow to you remember, the two מצוות Mitzvot *mitzvot* to
remember, you remember מצרים *Mitzrayim*, you remember שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, you somehow
you combine them together. If you look at תוספות Tosafot, *Tosfos* למען
תזכור את יום צאתך מארץ מצרים *Lema'an tizkor et yom tzetcha me'eretz
mitzrayim* לכך קבעו זכר ליציאת מצרים *Lekach kave'u zecher l'yetziat mitzrayim*. Right,
that's why it says in the קידוש Kiddush. *Kiddush*, right, זכר ליציאת
מצרים *Zecher l'yetziat mitzrayim*. ושמעתי מהמהר''ם *V'shamati mehaMaharam* שהיה במדרש *Shehaya bamidrash*
לפי שבמצרים עבדו בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael. בפרך *Lefi shebemitzrayim avdu Bnei
Yisrael befarech* ובפרך *Uvefarech* בא''ת ב''ש *b'Atbash* בגימטריא *begematria* הוא *hu* ל''ט
*lamed-tet* כנגד ל''ט מלאכות *keneged lamed-tet melachot*. You do the גימטריא *gematria*,
פרך *Parech* somehow gets you to thirty-nine. וכשנגאלו ממצרים הסיר מהם השבת
לשבות מאלו ל''ט מלאכות *Ucheshnig'alu mimitzrayim hesir mehem hashabbat lishbot me'elu lamed-tet
melachot*.
So it's a bit fancy way of saying what the תורה Torah
*Torah* already says, which is you were freed from being enslaved and
you are in charge now, you have the right to rest, you
do not have to do this work, and that's what שבת Shabbos
*Shabbat* is is the sense of this right to rest and to
know your freedom etc. So again it is funny, and I don't
have a really good explanation why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does not
connect it, you know, does not make it about that and makes
it more about this זכור *Zachor*. Now it's interesting the רשב''ם Rashbam
*Rashbam*, because Michael said well what about יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom
Tov*? By יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* also we mention זכר
ליציאת מצרים *Zecher l'yetziat mitzrayim*, right? So you know the תורה Torah
*Torah* actually does make that connection both you know by פסח Pesach
*Pesach* obviously and by סוכות *Succos*, כי בסוכות הושבתי *ki basuccot hoshavti*,
right? By שבועות *Shavuot*, not really. But if you take a look
at the רשב''ם Rashbam, *Rashbam*, right, the רשב''ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says צריך
שיזכיר יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim בקידוש היום *tzarich sheyazkir Yetziat Mitzrayim b'Kiddush
hayom*. I don't know where to tell you where it is, it's
about right in the middle there of the narrow lines. Line starts
with the word מצרים *Mitzrayim*. בין בכוס בין בתפילה *Bein b'kos bein
b'tefillah*. So first of all also mentions in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
*Shemoneh Esrei*. ששבת בגזירה שווה דפסח *SheShabbat b'gezeirah shavah de'Pesach* because the
פסוק *pasuk* is למען תזכור *Lema'an tizkor* and זכור את יום השבת
*Zachor et yom hashabbat*, you know למען תזכור *Lema'an tizkor* is by
פסח *Pesach*. ובשאר מועדים מנאמן מצינו מפסח *Uveshar moadim mineman matzinu miPesach*.
Okay so actually you know so and once we get that you're
supposed to mention it on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, you know, well you
mention on פסח *Pesach*, you mention it some גזירה שווה *gezeirah shavah*
on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* as well, which is why
in all of the קידושים *Kiddushes* we say זכר ליציאת מצרים *Zecher
l'yetziat mitzrayim*. But the one that really needs the only defending I
would say is you know is שבועות *Shavuot* and it is very
strange the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* connects it. Unless the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* wants to underscore, you know what, it's not just the
theme, there's an obligation to remember this part of the theme of
שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* based on the פסוק *pasuk* of למען תזכור *Lema'an
tizkor*. But again interesting how does the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* get there.
Rabbi, how did you read תוספות *Tosfos*? ובפרך *Uvefarech* בא''ת ב''ש *b'Atbash*?
What was that?
I don't want to do א''ת ב''ש *Atbash*. א''ת ב''ש *Atbash* is
a way of doing letter substitution in גימטריא *gematria* and so. That's
כבכ''בב''ש *kebachbebash*. Oh no, גל *Gal*.
Oh א''ת ב''ש ג''ל *Atbash Gal*?
No I'm sorry it was א''ת ב''ש *Atbash* gets you right, I
misread it. It was פרך *Parech* through א''ת ב''ש *Atbash* gets you
וגל *v'Gal*. I misread it. The פ *peh* becomes a ו *vav*,
the ר *resh* becomes a ג *gimmel*, I misread it, the כ
*khaf* becomes a ל *lamed*. And וגל *v'Gal* is thirty-nine. Okay fine.
And that's the מהר''ם *Maharam* of Rothenburg?
Presumably. I'd have to check. Presumably. That's pretty late for תוספות *Tosafos*
to be quoting it, so could be a different one. Okay I'd
have to check. אמר רבא Amar Rava, בר שילא *Amar Rava bar
Shila* דצלותא d'tzalota, *ditzluta* in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei* we
say מצמיח קרן ישועה matzmiach keren yeshuah? *Matzmiach keren yeshuah*. Again in
the present God causes the horn of redemption to sprout forth. דהפטרתא
*Dehafatarta* in הפטרה Haftarah, *Haftorah* we say when we make a ברכה
beracha *bracha* at the end of הפטרה *Haftorah* מגן דוד Magen David,
*Magen David*. So they're both about דוד David *David* and you know
and one is looking to the future where דוד *David*'s the future
בית דוד *Beit David* will have ascendancy again in the מלכות *Malchus*,
whereas the other's referring to the past about God has protected דוד
*David*. Now why exactly is that the difference? מגן Magen? *Magen* is
also in the present like we say מגן אברהם Magen Avraham, *Magen
Avraham*. So why not say you know מגן דוד Magen David *Magen
David*? What is the difference there? So let's take a look as
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues here. ועשיתי לך שם גדול gadol כשם
הגדולים *Ve'asiti lecha shem gadol keshem hagedolim*. So God says to דוד
*David* I will make for you a great name like the name
of the great ones. So where else did God say something about
making a great name? תני רב יוסף *Tani Rav Yosef* זהו שאומרים
מגן דוד Magen David *zehu she'omrim Magen David*. So we say מגן
דוד *Magen David* that God we identify God with דוד *David*. But
that's like כשם הגדולים *keshem hagedolim*. Which is כשם הגדולים *keshem hagedolim*?
מגן אברהם Magen Avraham *Magen Avraham*. And what did God say to
אברהם Avraham *Avraham*, right? ואעשך לגוי גדול ve'asecha l'goy gadol *Ve'esecha l'goy
gadol*, right, ואגדלה שמך *ve'agadlah shemecha*. So and that's כשם הגדולים *keshem
hagedolim*. You get the same status as אברהם Avraham, *Avraham*. אמר amar
רבי שמעון בן לקיש *Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish* ואעשך לגוי גדול
gadol *ve'esecha l'goy gadol* זהו שאומרים אלוהי אברהם Avraham. *zehu she'omrim Elohei
Avraham*. So interesting. the whole association of גוי גדול goy gadol, is
that the association of God with אברהם Avraham is the גוי גדול,
so great in sort of in name and status. וברכך u'varechecha זהו
שאומרים אלהי יצחק. zehu she'omrim Elohei Yitzchak. וגדלה שמך u'gadlah shemecha זהו
שאומרים אלהי יעקב. zehu she'omrim Elohei Yaakov. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says,
so
it's not exactly clear how you get that, but the מהרש"א Maharsha
says is that וה' ברך את יצחק, v'Hashem berach et Yitzchak, ויהי
אחרי מות אברהם vayehi acharei mot Avraham ויברך אלהים את יצחק בנו.
vayivarech Elohim et Yitzchak beno.
So
וברכך u'varechecha when you actually get the ברכה beracha is mentioned by
יצחק. Yitzchak. So God, sort of the truth of God's promise for
וברכך, u'varechecha, you see played out by יצחק. Yitzchak. And ואעשך לגוי
גדול I'm trying to remember, oh, he ties it in by יעקב.
Yaakov. How does he tie it? Well, clearly anyway יעקב Yaakov is
the one that has twelve children. He ties it in in a
different way. But anyway he sort of sees that it's because that
the promise gets fulfilled, so we say אלהי יצחק Elohei Yitzchak because
the truth of God's promise you could see was fulfilled by יצחק.
Yitzchak. That's the way the מהרש"א Maharsha reads it. יכול יחתמו בכולם,
yachol yachatmu bechulam,
maybe when you make the final ברכה beracha, in the שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei you should say ברוך אתה ה' מגן אברהם יצחק ויעקב.
Baruch atah Hashem Magen Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov. תלמוד לומר והיה ברכה. talmud
lomar v'heyeh berachah. There shall be a ברכה, beracha. maybe one ברכה.
bracha והיה v'heyeh not והיו, v'hayu, singular. בך חותמין ואין חותמין בכולן.
becha chotmin v'ein chotmin bechulan. And
you, אברהם, Avraham are the one that we emphasize at the end.
That's the beginning of the relationship. That's the מגן אברהם, Magen Avraham
the focus is on אברהם. Avraham. So if אברהם gets a מגן
אברהם and דוד gets a מגן דוד, that is a כשם הגדולים
אשר בארץ. k'shem hagedolim asher ba'aretz. Now, why the difference about מגן
דוד by, which is also in the present, in the הפטרה, as
opposed to מצמיח קרן ישועה? matzmiach keren yeshuah So the רשב"ם Rashbam
says, if you take a look at the
רשב"ם, Rashbam באפטרתא b'aftarta about a third from the end of the
narrow line, מסכת סופרים תניא להו לברכות דאפטרתא Masechet Soferim tanya lehu
l'virchot d'aftarta מפרש ומגן דוד אומר, mefaresh u'Magen David omer, ובתפלה שייך
לומר טפי מצמיח קרן ישועה u'v'tefillah shayach lomar t'fei matzmiach keren yeshuah
משום דרחמי נינהו mishum d'rachamei ninhu ואנן בעינן שיצמיח קרן ישועה לישראל.
v'anan ba'inan sheyatzmiach keren yeshuah l'Yisrael.
So not a difference of past and present, but about what we're
actually saying. מצמיח קרן ישועה matzmiach keren yeshuah. looks towards a future
flowering of the redemption, whereas מגן דוד is a pretty static, even
if the verb is the same tense, it's a much more of
a static idea than מצמיח קרן ישועה. yeshua And then he has
another explanation. רבנו שלמה היה אומר, Rabbeinu Shlomo hayah omer, presumably רש"י,
Rashi, משום הכי לא שייך למימר בצלא מגן דוד mishum hachi lo
shayach l'meimar b'tzalla Magen David שכבר אמרנו מגן אברהם. shekvar amarnu Magen
Avraham. ותרי חתימות כהדדי לא
שייך
בצלא. u'trei chatimot k'hadadi lo shayach b'tzalla. So we don't want to
be sound too redundant, so we have to have some different type
of a language. The first answer was a little bit nicer. They
could both be true.
Okay, and let's move back to actually the end of מגן אברהם
instead of saying ברוך אתה ה' אלהי
אברהם.
Baruch atah Hashem
Elohei Avraham.
Right? Why מגן? You have a good question, but let's bracket. I
think it comes up in ברכות, Berachot, and so yes, that's but
good question. So now the גמרא Gemara goes back. אמר amar רבא,
Rava אשכחינהו לסבי דפומבדיתא, ashchechinhu l'sava d'Pumbedita, I found the elders of
פומבדיתא Pumbedita דייתבי וקאמרי, d'yatvi v'ka'amri, they were sitting and saying. בשבתא,
b'shabta, on Shabbos, בין בצלותא בין בקידושא, bein b'tzalota bein b'kidusha, whether
in your שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei whether in your קידוש, Kiddush מקדש
השבת, mekadesh hashabbat, you say
מקדש
השבת, mekadesh hashabbat, which is what we do. ביום טוב, b'yom tov,
on Yom Tov, בין בצלותא בין בקידושא, bein b'tzalota bein b'kidusha, whether
in your שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei, whether in your קידוש, Kiddush מקדש
ישראל והזמנים, mekadesh Yisrael v'hazmanim, מקדש ישראל והזמנים, mekadesh Yisrael v'hazmanim, the
times, this is exactly what we say. ואמינא להו אנא, v'amina lehu
ana,
and I רבא Rava said back to them,
אדרבה, adarava, the opposite, not the exact opposite, but anyway דצלותא, d'tzalota,
it shouldn't be based on Shabbos versus Yom Tov, it should be
based on שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei, versus קידוש. Kiddush Really, אדרבה, adarava,
דצלותא, in שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei. בין בשבתא ובין ביומא טבא, bein
b'shabta u'vein b'yoma tava, whether Shabbos or Yom Tov, מקדש ישראל. mekadesh
Yisrael. Okay,
you always say מקדש ישראל, mekadesh Yisrael, you don't mention Shabbos, you
don't mention Yom Tov, you just mention מקדש ישראל. mekadesh Yisrael. בקידושא,
b'kidusha, in קידוש, Kiddush דשבתא d'shabta מקדש השבת, mekadesh hashabbat, ביומא טבא
b'yoma tava מקדש ישראל והזמנים. mekadesh Yisrael v'hazmanim.
So
actually the difference of מקדש השבת mekadesh hashabbat versus מקדש ישראל והזמנים
mekadesh Yisrael v'hazmanim he maintains, but only in קידוש. Kiddush. שמונה עשרה,
Shemoneh Esrei none of that. It's all מקדש ישראל. mekadesh Yisrael. Now
the גמרא Gemara explains. ואנא אמינא טעמא דידי וטעמא דידהו, v'ana amina
ta'ama didi v'ta'ama did'hu,
I can tell you my reason and I know what your reason
is.
Okay. טעמא דידהו, ta'ama did'hu,
your reason, which is what we do. שבת דקביעא וקיימא, shabbat d'kevi'a
v'kayama, Shabbos the קדושה Kiddusha
exists by itself, it's established and it exists. בין בצלותא בין בקידושא
bein b'tzalota bein b'kidusha מקדש השבת. mekadesh hashabbat.
So God is מקדש השבת, mekadesh hashabbat, ישראל Yisrael doesn't have a
place in that, that exists independently. יומא טבא, yoma tava, on Yom
Tov, דישראל הוא דקבעי ליה, d'Yisrael hu d'kavei leih, Yom Tov
the ישראל Yisrael that establishes Yom Tov דקמעברי ירחי וקבעי לשני, d'kam'avrei
yarchai v'kavei l'shani,
they decide when the months are 29 days or 30 days and
they decide the years whether there's going to be an extra month
in the year, they fix the calendar. So they have a role
in it. מקדש ישראל והזמנים, mekadesh Yisrael v'hazmanim, they God is מקדש
ישראל mekadesh Yisrael and through the role of ישראל Yisrael that. leads
to the partnership if you would leads to קדושת הזמנים. kedushat hazmanim.
Perfect. And that’s exactly what we do. טעמא דידי, Ta'ama didi, here’s
my reasoning why I think that yes you say that in קידוש
but you don’t say that in שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei Why do
I think שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is different?
צלותא דבי רבים, Tzeluta d'bei rabim, שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is done
in שול. shul. You know that’s its primary place to be done
in שול. shul. So therefore מקדש ישראל, Mekadesh Yisrael, so you want
to acknowledge everybody that’s gathered in שול, shul, you want to emphasize
God sanctifies His people ישראל Yisrael presumably people gather more in שול
shul on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov. than they do
during the week. So you want to emphasize that the קדושה kedusha
of the day and connects also you know the קדושה kedusha of
the people and give recognition to that מקדש
ישראל. Mekadesh Yisrael. קידושא דבי חבי, Kiddusha d'bei chavi, but קידוש takes
place in private.
Fine. בשבת מקדש השבת ביום טוב מקדש ישראל והזמנים. B'Shabbos Mekadesh HaShabbat,
b'Yom Tov Mekadesh Yisrael vehazmanim. I get the difference between שבת Shabbos
and יום טוב Yom Tov but basically I want to emphasize when
כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael when the community gets together on שבת Shabbos
and יום טוב Yom Tov and they all come to שול shul
and דאוון, daven, we should say מקדש ישראל Mekadesh Yisrael and somehow
you know emphasize the unique nature of the קדושת ישראל. kedushat Yisrael.
Fascinating because you know again it's not like קדושת ישראל kedushat Yisrael
is connected not trying to make an argument connected to קדושת השבת
kedushat HaShabbat right? It’s just that it’s like you know underscores maybe
that it’s an opportunity and where you have כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael
there and you want to acknowledge the קדושה kedusha of ישראל. Yisrael.
Or but obviously there would be a way to somehow say that
that would get heightened or reinforced through the קדושת השבת. kedushat HaShabbat.
This is that the ברכה bracha is really about Israel’s observance of
the holiday. Right.
And he make the point שבת Shabbos comes regardless of you know
בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael מקדש השבת Mekadesh HaShabbat that מקדש ישראל Mekadesh Yisrael that
we through our observance of שבת Shabbos our קדושה kedusha somehow demonstrated
or we're מקדש mekadesh something like that. Yeah.
Well he make the point that שבת Shabbos comes regardless. Right. So
that was including בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael. in the observance of שבת
Shabbos? whereas the ימים טובים Yamim Tovim it's required that בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael Right.
I mean it’s nice that you get בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael right.
So you’re sort of so it’s sort of the in a sense
the ברית bris of שבת Shabbos. between כי אות היא ki ot
hi you know you know because it's the אות ot and the
ברית bris between God and בני ישראל Yisrael so you want to
emphasize the role of ישראל Yisrael and the מקדש ישראל. Mekadesh Yisrael.
It's a nice point you know again he just says ברבים berabim
but maybe what you’re and I sort of tried to say maybe
it’s just the fact that everybody’s gathered but what you’re trying to
say is ברבים berabim gives us the opportunity to emphasize the you
know the role of ישראל in שבת Shabbos. as well. It could
be you know Rav Soloveitchik also speaks a lot about how the
קידוש that we make on שבת Shabbos although שבת Shabbos is you
know קביעא וקיימא kavia v'kayama that the קידוש that we do is
also itself our adding a level of קדושה kedusha to the קדושה
kedusha of שבת Shabbat and certainly that aspect of ברית bris is
there. So that’s what he says that you want to use that
as an opportunity to speak towards קדושת ישראל. kedushat Yisrael. Right.
Yeah.
Despite the idea that שבת Shabbat exists outside of ourselves who are
the ones that are commanded to observe שבת?
Shabbat Right. Right. Exactly. So we are definitely the ones who observe
it.
Okay. So that’s what he says so I accept the point that
it’s not just that we’re all together but it gives us the
opportunity to talk about our relationship to שבת. Shabbat I guess it's
funny that we ignore שבת. Shabbat. We just say מקדש ישראל. Mekadesh
Yisrael. We ignore יום טוב. Yom Tov We just say מקדש ישראל.
Mekadesh Yisrael. But okay. That’s what he says. And then the גמרא
Gemara says he says here ולא היא. v'lo hi. That’s actually not
a good argument. צלותא ביחיד מי ליתא? Tzeluta b'yachid mi leita? What
you don’t דאוון daven שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei ביחידות? b'yechidus? קידושא ברבים
מי ליתא? Kiddusha b'rabim mi leita? You never make קידוש ברבים? Kiddush
b'rabim? So then you cannot make that as the difference. ורבא סבר
אזיל בתר עיקר. V'Rava savar azil batar ikar. Rava says no you
go by their primary role. עולא בר רב נחית קמיה דרבא. Ulla
bar Rav nachit kamei d'Rava. עולא בר רב Ulla bar Rav went
in front of Rava. Went down means that he went to דאוון
daven שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei the שליח ציבור. shaliach tzibbur.
You have the language that is used is יורד לפני התיבה yored
lifnei hateivah and you are עולה oleh for an עליה aliyah on
the תורה. Torah When you read the תורה Torah it was from
a platform because you were reading דבר השם devar Hashem like from
on high. When you went to pray it was in a sort
of like in a well you know in a low place exactly
because the sense of calling out to God from the depths. So
he was יורד. yored. Whether it always was literally doing that or
that was how that was just became the use of the verb
is not clear but that's why it speaks about נחית. nachit. He
went down to דאוון daven in front of רבא Rava to be
the שליח ציבור. shaliach tzibbur. אמר כסבי דפומבדיתא. Amar k'sabei d'Pumbedita. So
there it was he was דאוונינג davening שמונה עשרה and he said
מקדש השבת Mekadesh HaShabbat or מקדש ישראל והזמנים. Mekadesh Yisrael vehazmanim. He
didn’t say מקדש ישראל. Mekadesh Yisrael. ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי v'lo
amar lei v'lo midi and רבא Rava did not interrupt him did
not object. אלמא הדר ביה רבא. Alma hadar bei Rava. You see
רבא Rava himself even reversed himself. רב נתן אבוה דרב הונא בריה
דרב נתן נחית קמיה דרב פפא. Rav Natan avua d'Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Natan nachit kamei d'Rav Papa. So another one who went down
in front of רב פפא. Rav Papa. אמר כסבי דפומבדיתא. Amar k'sabei
d'Pumbedita. He said like the others of פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. He said מקדש
השבת Mekadesh HaShabbat or he said מקדש ישראל והזמנים Mekadesh Yisrael vehazmanim
whichever it was. ושבחיה רב פפא. V'shabchei Rav Papa. And רב פפא
Rav Papa praised him. Oh beautiful exactly שמונה עשרה should be exactly
like קידוש. אמר רבינא. Amar Ravina. Said רבינא. Ravina. אנא איקלעי לסורא
קמיה דמרימר. Ana iklei l'Sura kamei d'Mareimar. I went to סורא Sura
in in front of מרימר Mareimar ונחית קמיה. v'nachit kamei. שלוחא דציבורא
shlucha de-tzibbura and the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur went out to דאווען
daven ואמר כסתבי דפומבדיתא v'amar kistavei d'Pumbedisa and he also said like
the elders of פומבדיתא Pumbedisa again whether it was if it was
שבת Shabbos, he said מקדש השבת Mekadesh Hashabbos was יום טוב Yom
Tov, מקדש ישראל והזמנים. Mekadesh Yisrael Vehazmanim. והוו משתקי ליה כולי עלמא
v'havu mashtikei lei kulei alma and everyone was saying shhh, no, no,
no, wrong thing. אמר להו amar lehu and then מרימר Marimar said
to them שבקויה shavkuya leave him alone הלכתא כסתבי דפומבדיתא hilchasa kistavei
de-Pumbedisa we rule like the elders of פומבדיתא Pumbedisa ולא הוו משתקי
ליה velo havu mashtikei lei and then they stopped silencing him. Or
if you look at the side an alternative גירסא girsa is והלכתא
כסתבי דפומבדיתא vehilchasa kistavei de-Pumbedisa then the anonymous voice of the גמרא.
Gemara But what it shows you what's important about this and always
to remember in cases around liturgy is that how much are debates
held just in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash or the debates in
the בית מדרש Beit Midrash reflect different practices that exist out there
particularly in areas of liturgy you know there clearly there were different
נוסחאות nuschaot and different types of practices and we saw it before
you know in areas we were discussing about אגוזי Agosi how היכי
עביד heichi avid how חז"ל Chazal אגוזי Agosi how he does this
and to some degree clearly here the whole people thought this guy
was making a mistake. It wasn't like everybody was taught by רבא
Rava necessarily. I mean it seems that maybe רבא Rava, himself was
maybe endorsing one approach and סתבי דפומבדיתא stavei de-Pumbedisa another. So you
have to wonder how much it was a top-down or bottom-up relationship
in terms of these issues of liturgy or like it was going
both ways. Yes. This discussion implies a later date for the codification
of
שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei than most that I've been taught in intro
classes. Look you know the basic structure we say is you know
אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesses Hagedolah but the גמרא Gemara itself and
the תוספתא Tosefta or whatever was aware of certain flux within certain
parameters. So yes the exact codification of you know text obviously is
over time. Okay so that was then a fascinating digression about aspects
of תפילה tefillah about the חתימת הגאולה chatimas hageulah at the end
of מגיד. maggid. Yes when exactly did the concept that you're not
allowed to change a word or add or you can't add שים
שלום Sim Shalom when did that concept of absolute frozenness of the
text when did that occur? I mean it's a good question. Yes
there were גאוני Geonic debates about additions that were added like for
around the ימים נוראים Yamim Noraim like עשרת ימי תשובה Aseres Yemei
Teshuva and that you're not supposed to add to the first three
ברכות brachos at all.
I mean the
גמרא Gemara and
then the question is can you
do it by צרכי ציבור tzarchei tzibbur and can you do it
for and you know whatever. But the גמרא Gemara does speak about
not adding to the first three ברכות brachos and making additions to
the middle ברכות. brachos. You raise a good question about the difference
between the actual standard text being in flux and operating within certain
parameters as opposed to something which is clearly an addition. Meaning it's
one thing if חז"ל Chazal say you know when you talk about
I don't know you know the ברכה bracha about רפאנו Refaeinu you
know it works within these parameters and so you have something that
works within those parameters and I have something a little different that
works in those parameters. And that's different from saying this actually I'm
no claim that this is the text I just want to insert
this idea you know and but I think it's a good question.
You're right. At the same time the גמרא Gemara speaks about here's
where you can insert here's where you can't there's the parallel reality
that the actual text itself had not been fully crystallized. That is
true. But I don't think you see anybody sort of I think
what you therefore see is people endorsing this is an acceptable נוסח
nusach because this was a text that was around you know at
this period and the text had not exactly sort of crystallized this
way as opposed to that way. I don't you know anyway I
think it's different than the question of insertion about what is the
acceptable נוסח nusach and then where can you make your own types
of insertions. ונתנה תוקף U-netanneh Tokef and וציפור Tzippur I mean there
are over entire other liturgies that not everyone accepts in ונתנה תוקף.
U-netanneh Tokef. Yes that's חזנות chazzanus chat that's- that's different. Okay.
But it is a very good question. I mean I'll just say
for example the ברכה bracha that we make at the end of
since you're talking about ימים נוראים Yamim Noraim at the end of
שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei a lot of people make עושה השלום Oseh
Hashalom right? רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik was very against that and I
don't say them and I'm not that the ישיבה Yeshiva doesn't say
them it says המברך את עמו ישראל בשלום Ha-mevarech es ammo Yisrael
bashalom עושה השלום Oseh Hashalom as opposed to המברך את עמו ישראל
בשלום Ha-mevarech es ammo Yisrael bashalom at the end of שמנה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei because you know the גמרא Gemara never indicates you change
the ברכה Bracha and there's no basis
for changing you know the ברכות brachos that the גמרא Gemara, doesn't
say you change. You know even the גאונים Geonim they inserted זכרנו
Zachrenu or whatever but not to change the נוסח הברכה. nusach habracha.
But then I found that actually in some גניזה Geniza fragments for
the תפילות tefillot for during the year forget ימים נוראים Yamim Noraim
they had עושה השלום Oseh Hashalom that it actually was a parallel
alternative text. And therefore what happened presumably was that on ימים נוראים
Yamim Noraim that... that version was endorsed. So I think that there's
again a difference between sort of seeing parallel texts that were around
and that there was some flux in terms of an absolute solidification
of only one text, which becomes sometimes perhaps legitimate alternatives, you know,
or could in theory be, as opposed to a question of insertions
and the גמרא Gemara says, you know, you don't make insertions in
the first three. But yeah.
Even today, I have a difference between the Artscroll and the Koren.
How about אשכנז Ashkenaz and ספרד? Sefarad?
I mean this is both supposedly נוסח אשכנז. Nusach Ashkenaz.
All right. All right. Let's move on. משנה Mishna now. So we've
got to the ברכה bracha at the end of מגיד. Maggid. Now
we get to מוזגו לו כוס שלישי, Mozgu lo kos shlishi, pouring
the cup of ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. We skipped over something. What
did we skip? Oh, forget שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. What did we
skip over?
מצה, Matzah, מרור, Maror, כורך. Korech. So the גמרא Gemara sort of
got to them and discussed them in passing, but it's quite fascinating
that the משנה Mishna completely leapfrogs over the big מצוות of אכילה
Achila and of the
שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. I don't know what to
say.
I don't know what to say about the flat fact that it
leapfrogs over that. מוזגו לו כוס שלישי, Mozgu lo kos shlishi, מברך
על מזונו. Mevarech al mezono. So you make ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon.
Okay. רביעי, Revi'i, it sounds like the משנה Mishna is very focused
on getting you done with your כוסות. Kosos. It seems like there's
this structure: מוזגו לו כוס ראשון, Mozgu lo kos rishon, מוזגו לו
כוס שני וכן הבן שואל, Mozgu lo kos sheni vechan haben shoel,
מוזגו לו כוס שלישי, Mozgu lo kos shlishi, like that's structuring the
rhythm here. Why don't you tell me you do מצה, Matzah, you
do מרור, Maror, you do ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, then you get
to your כוס? Kos? Like no, the כוסות Kosos are structuring the
narrative here. מוזגו לו כוס רביעי, Mozgu lo kos revi'i, you then
you pour the fourth cup, גומר עליו את ההלל Gomer alav et
ha-Hallel and that's where you finish ההלל Hallel you began at the
end of מגיד. Maggid. And that's הלל. Hallel. ואומר עליו ברכת השיר,
Ve'omer alav Birkat Hashir, and you end הלל Hallel with ברכת השיר.
Birkat Hashir. We'll see what that is in a minute.
בין הכוסות הללו,
Bein hakosos hallalu, between the earlier cups, between two and three and
presumably one and two, אם רוצה לשתות ישתה, Im rotze lishtot yishte,
you can drink. בין שלישי לרביעי לא ישתה, Bein shlishi li-revi'i lo
yishte, not between three and four. What's the difference between three and
four? So the רשב"ם Rashbam quotes the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says you'll
get drunk. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says you'll get drunk. So how
about the first three? You're already drunk, especially if you've been drinking.
And he says, no, no, no, drinking during the meal doesn't get
you drunk, at least that's between two and three. Drinking after the
meal gets you drunk. One could also speak about the issue about
not wanting to wash away the whole taste of the מצה Matzah
because by that time you're done with מצה, Matzah, אפיקומן, Afikoman, and
so
on. But, you know, but anyway the reason is not said. That
certainly could be and we'll discuss some of that when we get
to the idea of אין מפטירין אחר הפסח אפיקומן. Ein maftirin achar
hapesach afikoman. And I should say by the way again about the
fact that the משנה Mishna has completely jumped over what you do
during the meal is that you could have said, well, it doesn't
have to say the meal, that's obvious. It doesn't have to say
מצה Matzah and מרור, Maror, that's obvious. But you know what's not
obvious? What's not obvious is the whole thing we do about אפיקומן
Afikoman after we've done מצה. Matzah. Right? Why do we do two
מצות? Matzot? What's אפיקומן Afikoman about? None of that's in the משנה.
Mishna. So we'll see that in a minute. We'll see that later,
but I want to just acknowledge that. Okay, let's take a look.
Yeah, it could be actually that the משנה Mishna does refer to
eating at the beginning of the second cup. הביאו לפניו Hevi'u lefanav
חזרת Chazeret and
הביאו לו מצה
וחזרת וחרוסת ושני תבשילים.
Hevi'u lo
matzah vechazeret vecharoset ushnei tavshilin.
Maybe
that's when and גופו של פסח. Gupo shel pesach.
You want to read הביאו לפניו Hevi'u lefanav and you ate it
then?
Yeah, and then you did מגיד. Maggid.
That eating was first? I do think there are some scholars that
speculate on that, that in the משנה Mishna maybe the eating of
the מצה Matzah and the מרור Maror were all way up front.
Although it's a little bit funny that you're not doing ברכת המזון,
Birkat Hamazon, right, that you would wait all the time and the
כוס שני Kos sheni would be all on whatever, and then you'd
do מגיד. Maggid. It's part of eating, you're eating as you're telling.
That would make life a lot easier.
I do think there are some scholars that speculate on that and
that's a very good point. If the משנה's Mishna not mentioning when
you do מצה Matzah and מרור, Maror, maybe they did it way
much earlier. Yeah, could be.
And מה נשתנה Ma nishtana means anything?
No,
מה נשתנה Ma nishtana presumably means why. Okay, all right. So we
have, we'll discuss it when we do אפיקומן. Afikoman. Let's take a
look. אמר ליה רב חנה לרבא, Amar lei Rav Chana le-Rava, so
רב חנה Rav Chana said to רבא, שמע מינה ברכת המזון טעונה
כוס. Shma mina Birkat Hamazon te'una kos. Since it says you have
to make the third cup is on ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, you
see the general rule is you need to do ברכת המזון Birkat
Hamazon on a כוס, Kos, something we've discussed before that other גמרות
Gemarot seem to take for granted, but we know it's debated. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, not necessarily. ארבע כסי
תיקנו רבנן דרך חירות. Arba kasei tiknu rabanan derech cheirut. The rabbis
wanted to have four cups דרך חירות. derech cheirut.
כל חד וחד נעביד ביה מצוה, Kol chad vechad na'avid bei mitzvah,
wanted to ensure that each one you used it for a מצוה.
mitzvah. You didn't just סתם stam drink, that it had a ritual
placement, it was associated with a מצוה. mitzvah. So we decided do
this with ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. Doesn't mean generally we do it
with ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, but here was a way to ritually
place this כוס Kos associated with ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. I should
say though that this גמרא Gemara. makes it clear, which was not
really clear earlier, that the idea of four is דוקא, davka, meaning
it's saying because if it just said we wanted to have you
drink a lot דרך חירות, derech cheirut, then you wouldn't say well
why. Okay, and now we get to the fourth, רביעי אומר עליו
גומר עליו את ההלל. Revi'i omer alav gomer alav es ha-Hallel. And
אומר עליו ברכת השיר, omer alav Birchas ha-Shir, and you say the
ברכת השיר. Birchas ha-Shir. Let's take a look. מאי ברכת השיר? Mai
Birchas ha-Shir? What is this ברכה bracha of the שיר shir that
you say at the end of הלל? Hallel? רבי יהודה אומר יהללוך
השם אלוקינו, Rebbi Yehuda omer Yehallelucha Hashem Elokeinu, which is the ברכה
bracha we say at the end of הלל, Hallel, right? יהללוך השם
אלוקינו. Yehallelucha Hashem Elokeinu. I'll open up, I brought my הגדה Haggadah
with us today, because of this whole question of how do you
end the הלל Hallel here. Please don't get חמץ chametz on this.
Okay. יהללוך השם אלוקינו כל מעשיך וחסידיך צדיקים עושי רצונך Yehallelucha Hashem
Elokeinu kol ma'asecha vachasidecha tzaddikim osei ritzonecha etc. etc. כי
לעולם
ולעולמי
עולמים
אתה אל, ברוך אתה השם מלך מהולל בתשבחות.
ki
l'olam
u-l'olamei
olamim
atah
El,
Baruch
atah
Hashem
Melech
mehullal
batishbachos.
That's
how
you normally
end הלל. Hallel.
So he says ברכת השיר Birchas ha-Shir just means
the normal ברכה bracha. at
the end of הלל. Hallel. Now the ראשונים Rishonim ask, why would
you have
to say it? Why,
of course you should end with the ברכה. bracha No, not necessarily,
because the גמרא Gemara was never clear whether you begin הלל Hallel
in the middle of מגיד, Maggid, you begin it with the ברכה
bracha. אשר קדשנו. Asher kiddeshanu. It never said you begin with the
ברכה. bracha And some said nevertheless, if you're saying הלל, Hallel, you
begin with the ברכה bracha. like you always begin with the ברכה.
bracha? So one of the proofs that that's not true, besides that
it never says it, is that then why would you have to
say you end it with a ברכה? bracha, If you began with
a ברכה, bracha. of course you end it with a ברכה. bracha
So it's the only reason it would say here you end it
with a ברכה bracha is because it didn't begin that way and
because it's an exception. Okay, so that's, I wanted to just point
that out that it is, you know, it is debated, but we
assume and this is how we practice clearly and there's no hint
otherwise in the גמרא, Gemara, that the הלל Hallel initially starts without
a ברכה bracha. and that's very much because, how was that הלל
Hallel introduced? חייב לראות את עצמו, לפיכך אנחנו חייבים. Chayyav liros es
atzmo, lefichach anachnu chayyavim. If you're experiencing it, it's coming from this
internal impetus and it's not coming from this formal external obligation of
אשר קדשנו. Asher kiddeshanu. So we don't open it with a ברכה.
bracha Nevertheless, by the time we get to the end, maybe then
we are a little bit
more removed. We're not in that moment of גאולה. ge'ulah. We are
more, we've eaten, we're done, we're now looking past, back at it,
you know, we said אשר גאל ישראל, Asher ga'al Yisrael, it was
in the past, we shifted. So now we're doing it more as
a ritual and now we can do this ברכה bracha of ending
it with מלך מהולל בתשבחות. Melech mehullal batishbachos. Okay, and we end
it with, so that's what he says, you end it with the
normal ברכה bracha of הלל. Hallel. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rebbi Yochanan amar,
Rebbi Yochanan says, נשמת כל חי. Nishmas Kol Chai. You actually do
not end, you end with the נשמת כל חי Nishmas Kol Chai
ברכה bracha. at the end of יום טוב Yom Tov? and שבת
פסוקי דזמרה, Pesukei d'Zimra, which ends with ישתבח, Yishtabach, right? And that
is the other ending we have, which ends with ישתבח Yishtabach and
then ישתבח, אל מלך גדול מהולל בתשבחות, אל ההודאות, אדון הנפלאות, הבוחר
בשירי זמרה, מלך אל חי העולמים, Yishtabach, El melech gadol mehullal batishbachos,
El hahoda'os, adon hanifla'os, habocher b'shirei zimrah, melech El chei ha'olamim, which
also ends in that God being praised בתשבחות. batishbachos. So according to
him, he says we don't just say the end of הלל, Hallel,
what's called הלל המצרי, Hallel ha-Mitzri, the normal הלל, Hallel, we also
say these other פסוקי דתהלים pesukei d'Tehillim and נשמת כל חי Nishmas
Kol Chai and we give it this special ברכה. bracha Now this
leads to a huge debate in the ראשונים. Rishonim. A, which one
do we פוסק pasken like? And B, to what degree is the
one who says נשמת כל חי Nishmas Kol Chai excluding the idea
of the normal end of הלל? Hallel? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says
that he's adding to it. You end הלל Hallel normally, מלך מהולל
בתשבחות, Melech mehullal batishbachos, יהללוך Yehallelucha etc. מלך מהולל בתשבחות, Melech mehullal
batishbachos, then you say נשמת כל חי Nishmas Kol Chai and ישתבח
Yishtabach and then you end with מלך חי העולמים. Melech chei ha'olamim.
So you say two ברכות. brachos. Okay, now other ראשונים Rishonim disagree,
it says ברכת השיר, Birchas ha-Shir, doesn't say two, it says one.
So they say, no, no, no, it's actually a debate and we
פוסק pasken like the second one and we only end it with
the ברכה bracha of ישתבח. Yishtabach. Okay, so if you take a
look and then there's other positions. So if you take a look
at why I brought it in, in our הגדה, Haggadah, this is
nice because it gives you both ספרדי Sephardi and אשכנזי Ashkenazi נוסח.
nusach. So you have the, you have the end of הלל, Hallel,
right? הודו להשם כי טוב כי לעולם חסדו. Hodu l'Hashem ki tov
ki l'olam chasdo. Now יהללוך, Yehallelucha, it says only אשכנזים Ashkenazim say
יהללוך Yehallelucha here, okay. The אשכנזים Ashkenazim say יהללוך, Yehallelucha, they do
not end with מלך מהולל בתשבחות. Melech mehullal batishbachos. According to the
רשב"ם we should end that and end the standard הלל Hallel as
we integrated it all so we do not have two ברכות, brachos,
we have one. Okay, so the אשכנזים Ashkenazim say it here, then
we have הלל הגדול, Hallel ha-Gadol, כי לעולם חסדו. ki l'olam chasdo.
We'll get to that in a minute, how הלל הגדול Hallel ha-Gadol
gets inserted here, that's called הלל הגדול. Hallel ha-Gadol. Okay, then we
have נשמת כל חי, Nishmas Kol Chai, which is what we're talking
about. So you have the נשמת, Nishmas, etc. etc. ישתבח. Yishtabach. Now
what do you do? So if you're אשכנז, Ashkenaz, you end with
the normal ברכה Bracha that ends of ישתבח. Yishtabach. If you're ספרד,
Svard, okay, what do you do? You say here you have the
ישתבח, Yishtabach, and then here you have the יהללוך Yehalelucha paragraph here.
Not the יהללוך Yehalelucha back there. It also says we do both,
but we do both not first יהללוך Yehalelucha and ending with נשמת,
Nishmat, but נשמת Nishmat ending with יהללוך. Yehalelucha. And the ברכה Bracha
at the end is מלך מהולל בתשבחות, Melech Mehulal Batishbachot, the ברכה
Bracha, of יהללוך. Yehalelucha. So it's all very confusing. Do you do
the two things? The end of the normal הלל Hallel מלך מהולל
Melech Mehulal and then the ישתבח, Yishtabach, the end of נשמת? Nishmat?
That at least is easy. Okay, you've got two things going on
here. So you integrate them. And if you integrate them, so the
אשכנזים Ashkenazim say you integrate them and the end ברכה, Bracha the
one ברכה Bracha. you make is the ישתבח Yishtabach ברכה. Bracha And
the ספרדים Svardim say you integrate them and the end ברכה Bracha,
you make is the הלל Hallel ברכה, Bracha. is the יהללוך Yehalelucha
ברכה. Bracha So it's very confusing because you'll notice at this point
in the סדר, Seder, everybody is saying, "Wait, wait, what are you
saying? My הגדה Haggadah says something else." You know, nobody knows what's
going on. It's because of it's very terse in the גמרא Gemara
and leads to multiple מנהגים Minhagim here. Okay, so let's continue now.
The גמרא Gemara says like this. You know, before we go on,
maybe I'll just read one other thing about the נוסח Nusach about
the מנהגי הגדה. Minhagei Haggadah. If you look at תוספות, רביעי אומר
עליו הלל הגדול. Revi'i omer alav Hallel Hagadol. So he says רביעי
גרסינן דלא גרסינן חמישי Revi'i garsinan d'lo garsinan chamishi back on קטז
עמוד ב. Kuf Tet Vav Amud Bet. So apparently some had the
גרסא Girsah חמישי אומר עליו הלל הגדול. Chamishi omer alav Hallel Hagadol.
Okay, ורב יוסף טוב עלם שכתב בסדורו אם ירצה לשתות מים יכניס
עם כל החולי והסינית V'Rav Yosef Tov Elem shekatav besiduro im yirtzeh
lishtot mayim yachnis im kol hacholi vehasinit and so the poem. Anyway,
etc. Okay, he says תימא כיון שאסור לשתות איך תקנו כוס חמישי?
הא ארבע כוסות תקנו ולא חמישי. Teima keivan sheassur lishtot eich tiknu
kos chamishi? Ha arba kosot tiknu v'lo chamishi. And then he goes
on and on. But anyway, here you see that there's this whole
issue about A: is there a fifth כוס? Kos? We have the
כוס של אליהו, Kos shel Eliyahu, but I want you to be
aware that there's some question whether there's this obligation of actually drinking
a fifth כוס. Kos. It's not just a כוס של אליהו. Kos
shel Eliyahu. And then I want you to see at the end
he says why not to drink and the point I said about
the taste. ובהא דאמר בין שלישי לרביעי לא ישתה מפרש התם שלא
ישתכר ולא יוכל לומר הלל. וכן פסק רבינו שמואל לקמן דכל שתייה
מותרת ואפילו לפי המפרשים בין שלישי לרביעי לא ישתה משום דבטל טעמא
דמצה, מכל מקום במים לא מיירי אלא ביין. Uv'ha d'amar bein shelishi
l'revi'i lo yishte meforesh hatam shelo yishtaker velo yuchal lomar Hallel. Vechein
pasak Rabbeinu Shmuel lekaman dechol shtiah muteret v'afilu lefi hamefarshim bein shelishi
l'revi'i lo yishte mishum d'vateil ta'ama d'matzah, mikol makom bemayim lo mairi
ela beyayin. So here he has two other reasons, right? Is it
about being drunk or is it about the taste of מצה? Matzah?
And water would be fine, but other than water, how about all
other drinks between wine and water? If it's about being drunk it
would be okay. If it's about the taste of מצה Matzah it
would not be okay. Okay, so that is issues about the fourth—is
there a fifth כוס Kos and drinking after the third cup. Back
to the גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, רביעי
גומר עליו את ההלל ואומר הלל הגדול. Revi'i gomer alav et haHallel
v'omer Hallel Hagadol. So now we've mentioned נשמת Nishmat as a type
of a ending of the final ברכה Bracha, that you make, but
now we're introducing as we do after the הלל המצרי Hallel Hamitzri
before the נשמת, Nishmat, the idea of another type of a הלל.
Hallel. Not just a new ברכה, but another הלל, Hallel, the הלל
הגדול, Hallel Hagadol, which is the הודו לה' כי טוב. Hodu L'Hashem
Ki Tov. דברי רבי טרפון, Divrei Rabbi Tarfon, that's what Rabbi Tarfon
says. ויש אומרים ה' רועי לא אחסר, V'yesh omrim Hashem Ro'i Lo
Echsar, that there's, you know, the מזמור לדוד. Mizmor L'David. The רשב"ם
says it's connected to an ending of the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon
sort of trying to tie in the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon theme
like God protects me, provides for me, somehow with the הלל. Hallel.
It's a little strange but תערוך לפני שולחן. Ta'aroch l'fanai shulchan. תערוך
לפני, Ta'aroch l'fanai, exactly. I'll get back to that in a minute.
מהיכן הלל הגדול? Meheichan Hallel Hagadol? Where is הלל הגדול Hallel Hagadol
from? What constitutes—we know what הלל מצרי Hallel Mitzri is, the normal
הלל. Hallel. What's הלל הגדול? Hallel Hagadol? רב יהודה אומר מהודו עד
נהרות בבל. Rav Yehuda omer meHodu ad Naharot Bavel. What we say
הודו לה' כי טוב, Hodu L'Hashem Ki Tov, all the הודו Hodus
ending in נהרות בבל Naharot Bavel in the next פרק. Perek. Wow.
רבי יוחנן אומר משיר המעלות, Rabbi Yochanan omer meShir HaMa'alot, which is
two פרקים Prakim before the הודו לה' כי טוב Hodu L'Hashem Ki
Tov עד נהרות בבל. ad Naharot Bavel. רב אחא בר יעקב אומר
מכי יעקב בחר לו יה Rav Acha Bar Yaakov omer meKi Yaakov
bachar lo Yah עד נהרות בבל, ad Naharot Bavel, which is like
a half of a פרק Perek before. This is how we lead
into the הלל הגדול Hallel Hagadol in you know we say this
obviously in שבת and יום טוב Yom Tov, in the פסוקי דזמרה.
Psukei D'zimra. הודו לה' כי טוב, Hodu L'Hashem Ki Tov, right? And
we lead into it, we say the פרק Perek of תהילים Tehillim
that precedes it. Okay, we don't start from שיר המעלות, Shir HaMa'alot,
which is two פרקים Prakim earlier, but we do start from the
פרק Perek before it, which has in it כי יעקב בחר לו
יה. Ki Yaakov bachar lo Yah. So if we're going to which
components, clearly the הודו לה' כי טוב Hodu L'Hashem Ki Tov is
הלל הגדול. Hallel Hagadol. When we talk about this thing called הלל
הגדול, Hallel Hagadol, what does it all include? And there's this issue
here about how far back you go prior. Okay, we obviously go
by only the הודו לה' Hodu L'Hashem פרק. Perek. But you saw
ספרדים Svardim on שבת say שיר המעלות. Shir HaMa'alot. Oh, they do
say the שיר המעלות. Shir HaMa'alot. Oh, so the אשכנזים Ashkenazim just
start from the פרק Perek right before, but it's interesting that the
ספרדים Svardim go all— So למה נקרא שמו הלל הגדול? lama nikra
shemo Hallel HaGadol? Why is this called הלל הגדול? Hallel HaGadol? We
know why is this called הלל הגדול, Hallel HaGadol, right, the הלל
מצרי, Hallel Mitzri, what we call our standard הלל Hallel on יום
טוב, Yom Tov we call הלל מצרי Hallel Mitzri because, you know,
בצאת ישראל ממצרים. Betzeit Yisrael MiMitzrayim. Why is this called הלל הגדול?
Hallel HaGadol? אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan מפני שהקדוש ברוך הוא
יושב ברומו של עולם, mipnei sheHaKadosh Baruch Hu yoshev berumo shel olam,
God dwells up high, ומחלק מזונות לכל בריותיו, umachalek mezonot lechol beriyotav,
and provides for all creatures, right? Because what does it say in
the כי לעולם חסדו? ki le'olam chasdo? It says נותן לחם לכל
בשר כי לעולם חסדו. noten lechem lechol basar ki le'olam chasdo. And
the הודו לה׳ Hodu LaShem piece, and it's worth mentioning this, right,
you could also ask, and the גמרא Gemara is going to ask
in a minute, why do we say הלל המצרי Hallel HaMitzri on
the ימים טובים? Yamim Tovim? You could also ask, why do we
say the הלל הגדול Hallel HaGadol on every שבת and יום טוב?
Yom Tov? And the basic point of difference is, I mean, we'll
see this partly in the גמרא, is that the הלל הגדול, Hallel
HaGadol, while it has the mentions of יציאת מצרים, Yetziat Mitzrayim, right,
let me just find it, right, the הלל הגדול Hallel HaGadol has
in it, right, it says ויוצא ישראל מתוכם ביד חזקה ובזרוע נטויה
לגוזר ים סוף לגזרים, vayotzi Yisrael mitocham beyad chazaka uvizroa netuya legozer
yam suf legezarim, right, the יציאת מצרים Yitziat Mitzrayim, is all at
the end, but a significant part at the beginning is about the
God of creation and of the day-to-day, right, עושה נפלאות לבדו עושה
השמים את השמש את הירח, oseh niflaot levado oseh hashamayim et hashemesh
et hayareiach, right, you know, נותן לחם לכל בשר, noten lechem lechol
basar, so it's more of, not yes, it is יציאת מצרים, Yitziat
Mitzrayim. but it's also the translation of and the recognition of God
on the daily basis, whereas you don't have that same really in
the הלל המצרי. Hallel HaMitzri. The הלל המצרי Hallel HaMitzri is all
about, you know, the sort of very supernatural and miraculous salvation of
God. It's much more about salvation as opposed to God on the
sort of ongoing God as nature and God as provider. So on
a regular שבת and יום טוב, you know, it's a heightened time,
we have more time in שול, shul, heightened time to be aware
of God's presence, we'll talk about the God of, you know, nature,
the God as the provider, but you know, that's in the פסוקי
דזמרא. Pesukei DeZimra. But when you're going to say a הלל המצרי,
Hallel HaMitzri, you know, on those special occasions, you want to focus
more on the גאולה geula aspect. So I think it's important to
acknowledge those differences. Okay, and so therefore it says what makes it
גדול is that even though God is way up on high, God
takes care of every lowly creature. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi הני עשרין ושישה הודו כנגד מי? hani esrin
veshisha Hodu keneged mi? 26 times it says, you know, 26 lines
of refrain, הודו לה׳ כי טוב, Hodu LaShem ki tov, what does
the number 26, what's that corresponding to? Assuming that it was chosen
with specifically because of the number. כנגד כ״ו דורות שברא הקדוש ברוך
הוא בעולמו, keneged chaf-vav dorot shebara HaKadosh Baruch Hu beolamo, there are
26 generations from the time the world was created ולא נתן להם
תורה, velo natan lahem Torah, and there was no תורה Torah, until,
you know, the תורה Torah, is only given at the 26th generation
at הר סיני, Har Sinai, וזנם בחסדו, vezanam bechasdo, and נותן לחם
לכל בשר כי לעולם חסדו. noten lechem lechol basar ki le'olam chasdo.
God provided for all creatures even though they didn't merit it, even
though there was no תורה yet in the world. So again, this
emphasis of God making sure that every creature is provided for and
in a way the God of history, the God, I mean the
God of nature, you know, without the God of history and the
God of תורה, and that, that sort of ongoing presence. So that's
in a way what makes it truly גדול and also as I
said, in a way makes it something we say on a regular
שבת. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's
meant by הודו לה׳ כי טוב? Hodu LaShem ki tov? הודו לו
שגובה חובתו של אדם בטובתו, Hodu lo shegoveh chovato shel adam betovato,
that God is good that he, when we owe, when a person
has a debt to God, God collects the debt with something God
himself has given out of his, out of God's goodness. What does
this mean? עשיר בשורו, ashir beshoro, if a rich person sinned, rather
than that person suffering personally, God will take away the ox. דעני
בשיאו, de'ani besayo, if it's a poor person, the sheep. יתום בביצתו,
yatom bebetzato, an orphan, even more, you know, destitute, he'll take away
his egg, the egg he was to eat for breakfast. אלמנה בתרנגולתה,
almana betarnagoltah, a widow, her chicken. So God doesn't actually bring, you
know, when he has to collect his debts, as it were, he
does not, it's not, he only takes back something God himself has
given. Now, what's fascinating about this is, okay, besides that really, that's
all that happens, people don't suffer, okay, but anyway, bracketing that, what's
fascinating is, what I see happening is חז״ל Chazal take this whole
thing הודו לה׳ כי טוב כי לעולם חסדו. Hodu LaShem ki tov
ki le'olam chasdo. And you look around and sometimes, especially for the
time of חז״ל Chazal when they lived, a period of, you know,
persecution, a period where, where deprivation, כי לעולם חסדו, ki le'olam chasdo,
where do you see the כי לעולם חסדו? ki le'olam chasdo? And
the translation of that is amazing, is astounding. You know what's כי
לעולם חסדו? ki le'olam chasdo? Because נעבעך, nebach, you know, so so
so it's just that I don't have a lot of money, you
know, and that's amazing חסד chesed of God that all he did
was he took away, he took away my wealth and he didn't
take away, you know, he didn't hurt me personally. So you find
the חסד chesed even in the situations in which it's less obvious,
you know, and which it almost seems to be contradictory. And I
think that's like extremely powerful the way they are taking this amazing...
But I have to say that, you know, so health and life
and other things still come from God. Right, they do. So that's
another answer that חז״ל Chazal have. ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, you know,
that he's paying up my sins in עולם הזה Olam Hazeh so
I don't have to pay it up in עולם הבא. Olam Haba.
It's not what this גמרא is saying. I understand but I mean
what I think is amazing is the reaffirmation just by interpretation. It
doesn't even acknowledge the problem. Right, just by interpreting it, that affirmation
that we're always seeing God's חסד. chesed. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, קשה מזונותיו של אדם כפליים כיולדה. Kashe mezonotav shel adam kiflayim
kiyoledah. The challenges of making a פרנסה, parnassah, food, are twice as
difficult as giving birth. This is a man talking. דאילו ביולדה כתיב,
De'ilu beyoledah ketiv, by giving birth it says, בעצב, be'etzev, בעצב תלדי
בנים be'etzev teldi vanim in singular. ובמזונות כתיב, Uvimzonot ketiv, בעיצבון, be'itzavon,
which is seen as, you know, it really is singular but seen
as more sense of a plural so it's more difficult. Okay. ואמר
רבי יוחנן, Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan, קשה מזונותיו של אדם יותר מן הגאולה.
Kashe mezonotav shel adam yoter min hageulah. You know, making פרנסה's parnassah
harder than redemption or so much for not complaining. Right, right. Well,
no, but I want to say, I'll get back to that. Somehow,
but you know, like harder for who? Like nothing is hard for
God, but like it would be harder for us. Anyways, the miracle
of it, the ability of it is as great as that of
redemption or greater. דאילו בגאולה כתיב, De'ilu bageulah ketiv, המלאך הגואל אותי
מכל רע. Hamalach hagoel oti mikol ra. God only has to send
an angel to achieve redemption. מלאך דעלמא, Malach dealma, just an angel.
ואילו במזונות כתיב, Ve'ilu bimzonot ketiv, האלוקים הרועה אותי. HaElokim haro'eh oti.
And that's the idea of מזמור לדוד השם רועי, Mizmor LeDavid Hashem
Ro'i, God who shepherds me, who makes sure that I am provided
for. Now what I want to say is fascinating about they're not
complaining but you know they're sort of saying look at what God
does, I mean maybe there's a little bit of a recognition about
we have it hard but they're not saying but they're, you know,
but I think this ultimately sort of saying and we see that
it's coming from God. What I think is amazing is the way
this is being juxtaposed to the whole הגדה, Haggadah, which is all
about אפילו עני שבישראל לא יפחתו לו מארבע כוסות, Afilu ani shebeYisrael
lo yiphitu lo me'arba kosot, and at the same time we're sort
of like acknowledging in this discussion of הגדה, Haggadah, I'm not sure
if they're doing it on סדר Seder or not, but you know,
you know actually when we get back to the real world and
we leave little fantasy land tonight it's really hard just to put
food on the table. And you know and our גאולה geulah maybe,
you know, we talk about the גאולה geulah of מצרים, כשם אלוקיכם
יחינו, K'shem Elokeichem yihyeinu, you know, or whatever, גאל ישראל, Ga'al Yisrael,
maybe we have to appreciate the גאולה geulah that God manages to
provide for us on a day-to-day basis. So in a way it's
like this shocking transition from this little from this you know fantasy
of הסבה haseibah and יין yayin on ליל הסדר Leil HaSeder to
earning it to make pennies the next you know when you get
out into the real world but it's also a translation of it.
You know what, that's actually more challenging than גאולת מצרים. Geulat Mitzrayim.
And God's גאולת מצרים, Geulat Mitzrayim, we see God's גאולה geulah in
helping us make a פרנסה parnassah day to day. So again I
think it's this amazing way of trying to bridge this gap between
you know the פסוקים psukim and the reality and the sort of
actual the reenacting that you're doing and your challenges of the real
world but I don't see it as you said as complaining. I
see it as the way of seeing and look how God is
look at what God is doing and this is even more of
a נס nes than you see in מצרים. Exactly. So okay, so
now the גמרא says like this. Okay. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי,
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, בשעה שאמר הקדוש ברוך הוא לאדם, Besha'ah
she'amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu le'adam, קוץ ודרדר תצמיח לך, Kotz vedardar tatzmiach
lach, it'll you'll try to plow the land and it'll come up
thorns and thistles. זלגו עיניו דמעות, Zalgu einav dma'ot, his eyes flowed
with tears. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, he said to him, ריבונו של
עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, מה אני וחמורי נאכל באבוס אחד? Mah ani
vachamori nochel be'evus echad? Me and my donkey shall eat from the
same trough? We're all going to eat the you know the stuff
that grows from the ground? We're all the same? כיון שאמר לו,
Keivan she'amar lo, once God said to him, בזעת אפיך תאכל לחם,
Beze'at apecha tochal lechem, ah, by the sweat of your brow you'll
eat bread. Not grain, not the normal stuff, not the stuff that
grows naturally. You'll have to work for it but you'll transform it
into bread. נתקררה דעתו. Nitkarerah da'ato. Ah, he calmed down. Okay, I
gotta work, but at least I'm on a higher level than the
animals, I'm not eating the ground. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Resh Lakish,
so said Resh Lakish, אשרינו אם עמדנו בראשונה. Ashreinu im amadnu barishonah.
You know what? It would have been better, we would have been
praised if we would have just been able to eat the grass
and we wouldn't have to work so hard to turn it into
bread. You know? It's easier to live like the donkey. So this
is an interesting question right about the effort and the work and
the toil openly for that sense of human dignity about that what
you you know you actually produce something at this higher plane of
you know of of development and but it requires a lot of
effort. It would have been easier to just eat like an animal.
ועדיין לא פלטינן מינה. Ve'adayin lo paltinan minah. You know he says
don't kid yourself. Don't think like ah well we're on a different
plane from animals. That would have been easy and that would have
been good and even now when we make bread and we grind
wheat and all that we're still not out of the category of
animals. Why not? דקאכלינן עשבי דדברא, Dekachlinan ishvei dedabra, we still eat
the grass of the field meaning presumably vegetables or something. You know,
I you know. I'm sure we all know the people like who
says, "Vegetables? Like eating rabbit food?" or something. So this is like
that attitude, right? אוי, Oy, we still eat vegetables! You're not so
cultured. But again, it's this power sense about, you know what, the
effort it takes to achieve that sense of being cultured and dignity
and so on, as opposed to this easier, more natural existence. In
a way, that's the whole story of being driven out of גן
עדן. Gan Eden. You don't get to live like, you know, you
have to work to establish your sense of, you know, human dignity
and you don't just, you know, eat like without any effort, but
then, but also without any sense of, you know, of accomplishment. הלוואי
דפרנסיה ממאזא דבי ורישא דראשונה. Halevai deparnasiah mimaza devei reisha derishona. If
we would have been able to stick with the first way, we
would have just been כעשבא דארעא דצמחא, Ke-isba de-ar'a detzamcha, forget this
פסקא דאלף עלמא. paska de-alaf alma. We could have been just eating
like animals and not so to speak developed. Exactly. אמר רב שישי
משמיה דרבי אלעזר בן עזריה: קשה מזונותיו של אדם. Amar Rav Shishi
mishmeih de-Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah: Kasheh mezonotav shel adam. But by the
way, again notice how what this is doing is it's placing a
value on all of the effort we have to put in order
to make a living. Right? So it's acknowledging the harsh realities of
life. Before it was sort of saying, and notice how this is
what God is doing for you, it's קשיא מכריעת ים סוף. Kashya
mikri'at Yam Suf. And now it's also saying, and notice, you know,
okay, if you bracket that sense of we would have been better
the other way, but, you know, ultimately look how important this is
and what this achieves in terms of human dignity. אמר רב אלעזר
בן עזריה: קשה מזונותיו של אדם כקריעת ים סוף. Amar Rav Elazar
ben Azaryah: Kasheh mezonotav shel adam kekri'at Yam Suf. Now again the
tying in to יציאת מצרים, Yitziat Mitzrayim I think, is again bridging
this gap between פסח night and the rest of the year. It's
more challenging, whatever that means for God, you know, for us, not
for God, but anyway, the sustaining, a person earning a living than
the splitting of ים סוף. Yam Suf. דכתיב: נותן לחם לכל בשר,
כי לעולם חסדו. וסמיך ליה: לגוזר ים סוף לגזרים. Dechtiv: Noten lechem
le-chol basar, ki le'olam chasdo. Usemich lei: Legozer Yam Suf ligzarim. Right,
the juxtaposition of providing daily and קריעת ים סוף Kri'at Yam Suf
is in this הלל הגדול. Hallel HaGadol. By the way, I think
that's why the גמרא before also mentioned that the saying of השם
רועי לא אחסר. Hashem roi lo echsar. Again, the tying in of
God's providing. In a way, this providing is a bridge, as I
said, from the סדר Seder night to the rest of the year.
So it's this bridge of moving into the providing on a day-to-day
basis, connecting it to the יציאת מצרים. אמר רב אלעזר בן עזריה:
קשים נקביו של אדם, נקביו של אדם, Amar Rav Elazar ben Azaryah:
Kashim nekavav shel adam, nekavav shel adam, excuse me, כיום המיתה. keyom
hamitah. The man's orifices, meaning being able to go to the bathroom,
is as challenging as the day of death. וכקריעת ים סוף, Ukekri'at
Yam Suf, and like the splitting of the of the ים סוף.
Yam Suf. שנאמר: מהר צועה להפתח. Shene'emar: Miher tzo'eh lehipateach. Quickly will
the צועה, tzo'eh, which basically the רשב"ם says means the stuck one,
the constipated one, open up. וכתיב בתריה: רוגע הים ויהמו גליו. Uchtiv
batreih: Rogeh hayam vayehemu galav. God disturbs the ocean and its waves,
you know, roar. So that's basically קריעת ים סוף. Kri'at Yam Suf.
I'm not exactly sure about the יום המיתה. yom hamitah. ואמר רב
ששת משום אלעזר בן עזריה: Ve'amar Rav Sheshet mishum Elazar ben Azaryah:
Now since we're talking about רב אלעזר בן עזריה, Rav Elazar ben
Azaryah, this is a little bit of a digression from a digression.
כל המבזה את המועדות כאילו עובד עבודה זרה. Kol hamivazeh et hamo'adot
ke'ilu oved avodah zarah. Anybody who denigrates the יום טוב—and some say
specifically means חול המועד—is Chol HaMoed as bad as somebody who worships
idols. שנאמר: אלוהי מסכה לא תעשה לך. Shene'emar: Elohei masechah lo ta'aseh
lach. Don't make yourself molten gods. וכתיב בתריה: את חג המצות תשמור.
Uchtiv batreih: Et chag hamatzot tishmor. And that also, from there we
also learn aspects of חול המועד Chol HaMoed if you want to
read it that way. ואמר רב ששת משום רבי אלעזר בן עזריה:
Ve'amar Rav Sheshet mishum Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah: another statement of רב
ששת Rav Sheshet in the name of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah. כל המספר לשון הרע וכל המקבל לשון הרע. Kol
hamisaper lashon hara vechol hamikabel lashon hara. These are obviously very radical
comparisons. So until now it was: this is as big of a
miracle as קריעת ים סוף. Kri'at Yam Suf. Now it's the radical
comparison about how bad the sin is. Okay, כל המספר לשון הרע
וכל המקבל לשון הרע. Kol hamisaper lashon hara vechol hamikabel lashon hara.
If you tell or accept לשון הרע. lashon hara. וכל המעיד עדות
שקר בחבירו, Vechol hame'id edut sheker bechavero, or testify falsely against someone,
ראוי להשליכו לכלבים, ra'uy lehashlicho laklavim, deserves to be thrown to the
dogs. שנאמר: לכלב תשליכון אותו. Shene'emar: Lakelev tashlichun oto. It says by
the נבילה, neveilah, throw it to the dogs. וכתיב בתריה: לא תשא
שמע שוא. Uchtiv batreih: Lo tisa shema shav. Do not bear a
false report, a false name. וקרי ביה לא תשיא. Ukari beih lo
tashi. Doesn't only mean don't listen to one, it also means don't
cause one to be born, don't report falsely. Okay, now let's get
back to הלל הגדול Hallel HaGadol and הלל הגדול. Hallel HaGadol. וכי
מאחר דאיכא הלל הגדול, Vechai me'achar de'ika Hallel HaGadol, since there's this
amazing הלל הגדול Hallel HaGadol that has קריעת ים סוף Kri'at Yam
Suf and it has מזונותיו של אדם, mezonotav shel adam, so אנן
מאי טעמא אמרינן האי? anan mai ta'ama amrinan hai? Why do we
say the other one on the יום טוב? Why do we say
the one that we call the our our הלל? Hallel? משום שיש
בו חמישה דברים הללו. Mishum she-yesh bo chamishah devarim halalu. It has
five things: יציאת מצרים וקריעת ים סוף. vekri'at Yam Suf. Okay, הלל
הגדול Hallel HaGadol has that too. ומתן תורה ותחיית המתים וחבלו של
משיח. Umatan Torah u-techiyat hametim ve-chevlo shel mashiach. I bet you didn't
know those three were in there. יציאת מצרים דכתיב: בצאת ישראל ממצרים.
Yitziat Mitzrayim dechtiv: Betzet Yisrael mi-Mitzrayim. קריעת ים סוף דכתיב: הים ראה
וינוס. Kri'at Yam Suf dechtiv: Hayam ra'ah vayanos. Right, so which is
the the ocean right ran away, which is the splitting of the
ים סוף. Yam Suf. מתן תורה דכתיב: ההרים רקדו כאילים. Matan Torah
dechtiv: He-harim rakedu che-eilim. The mountains danced. So the מדרש Midrash of
course, you know, mountains evoke סיני Sinai and the whole world trembled.
Okay, תחיית המתים דכתיב: אתהלך לפני השם בארצות החיים. Techiyat hametim dechtiv:
Ethalech lifnei Hashem be'artzot hachayim. ארצות החיים. artzos hachayim. So the land
of the living where there is only life is תחיית המתים. Techiyas
HaMeisim. חבלו של משיח Chavlo shel Moshiach דכתיב, dechsiv, the birth pangs
of משיח Moshiach דכתיב dechsiv לא לנו ה׳ לא לנו. lo lanu
Hashem lo lanu. No, not for us, which means like it's going
to be difficult and challenging because the period leading up to משיח
Moshiach is one of suffering. ואמר רב יוחנן Va'amar Rav Yochanan לא
לנו ה׳ לא לנו lo lanu Hashem lo lanu זו שיעבוד מלכויות,
zu shibud malkhiyos, this is when the subjugation of the nations and
then we're freed from it at the times of משיח. Moshiach. איכא
דאמרי Ikka d'amri אמר רב יוחנן amar Rav Yochanan לא לנו ה׳
לא לנו lo lanu Hashem lo lanu זו מלחמת גוג ומגוג, zu
milchemes Gog uMagog, which is the actual war of leading up to
the coming of משיח. Moshiach. So this is what it says but
you know this is not really a fully satisfying answer. Okay, that's
got these things, that's got these things. Why do you pick one
at this time and one at the other time? Which is what
I said at the beginning that I think to go back to
the first thing the גמרא said, the הלל הגדול Hallel Hagadol is
the more God of nature, the God of מזונות, mezonos, plus the
miraculous God, plus the salvation God. So that's something to say on
a more regular basis being שבת, you know, in the פסוקי דזמרא
Pesukei D'zimra whereas the one that's all about God as salvation and
ישועה and miracles, that is the one that we say in the
הלל Hallel that we say on יום טובים. Yom Tovim. But also
I think very powerfully that is the bridge that we are making
on ליל סדר. Leil Seder. We're starting from the הלל הגדול, Hallel
Hagadol, I mean from the הלל המצרי, Hallel Hamitzri, from the miraculous
and the salvation, but now we've got to transition it into the
rest of the year and that's the הלל הגדול. Hallel Hagadol. Yes.
Yesterday we sang the לא לנו ה׳ לא לנו. lo lanu Hashem
lo lanu. Yeah, we're going to get back to it again. So
that was okay, yeah, it was ודאי. vadai. Yeah, I know, I
know. So there's different לא לנוs. lo lanu I want to read
a little bit more. Okay. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak אמר amar משום mishum יש בו מילוט נפשן של צדיקים מגיהנום,
yesh bo milut nafshan shel tzaddikim migehinnom, a few other things that
it has, the righteous are saved from גיהנום. Gehinnom. שנאמר shenemar אנא
ה׳ מלטה נפשי, Ana Hashem malta nafshi, save my soul, which means
from גיהנום. Gehinnom. חזקיה Chizkiyah אמר משום mishum יש בו ירידתן של
צדיקים לכבשן האש ועלייתן ממנו, yesh bo yeridasan shel tzaddikim l'kivshan haeish
v'aliyasan mimenu, the righteous going down into the fire and being saved,
again a type of salvation and particularly about חנניה מישאל ועזריה. Chananya
Mishael v'Azarya. This is going to be a whole play on the
לא לנו, lo lanu, so let's just get this to the end,
go a few extra minutes for those that can stay. Okay דכתיב
dechsiv ירידתן, yeridasan, going down, דכתיב dechsiv לא לנו ה׳ לא לנו.
lo lanu Hashem lo lanu. לא לנו lo lanu אמר חנניה. amar
Chananya. So חנניה Chananya said, no, don't do this for us, we
mean don't do it to us, not don't save us for our
own sake, don't do this to us. כי לשמך תן כבוד, Ki
l'shimcha ten kavod, do it for your sake, אמר מישאל, amar Mishael,
but this is what they're praying not to get thrown into the
כבשן האש. kivshan haeish. על חסדך ועל אמתך Al chasdecha v'al amittecha
אמר עזריה. amar Azarya. So חנניה מישאל ועזריה Chananya Mishael v'Azarya being
thrown into the fiery furnace. למה יאמרו הגוים Lamma yomru hagoyim אמר
כולם, amru kulam, right, why should the nations say you've abandoned us,
you've abandoned us, so don't let this happen. So they're praying not
to get thrown or they're praying to be saved, but it's a
prayer of request, of בקשה. bakasha. עלייתן מכבשן האש Aliyasan mikivshan haeish
where it turns from בקשה bakasha into praise, דכתיב dechsiv הללו את
ה׳ כל גוים. hallu es Hashem kol goyim. Okay אמר חנניה. amar
Chananya. שבחוהו כל האומים Shabbechu'u kol ha'umim אמר מישאל. amar Mishael. כי
גבר עלינו חסדו Ki gavar aleinu chasdo אמר עזריה. amar Azarya. So
now they all got saved, now they're all saying praises to God.
Right, it's sort of like the whole יונה Yonah story. You're in
the צרה, tzarah, you pray, you know, you have your תפילה, tefillah,
God saves you, you have the שבח. shevach. ואמת ה׳ לעולם הללויה
Ve'emes Hashem l'olam halleluyah אמרו כולם. amru kulam. Okay ויש אומרים veyesh
omrim ואמת ה׳ לעולם ve'emes Hashem l'olam גבריאל אמרו, Gavriel amro, גבריאל
Gavriel said it. Because when it says in the כבשן האש kivshan
haeish story there in דניאל, Daniel, it says they saw a fourth
person who looked like a fiery man coming and saving them. And
the angel of fire is גבריאל, Gavriel, so he's identified by חז״ל
Chazal as that figure that came and saved חנניה מישאל ועזריה. Chananya
Mishael v'Azarya. Let's just read this one story and end with this.
Okay גבריאל אמרו. Gavriel amro. בשעה שהפיל נמרוד הרשע את אברהם אבינו
לתוך כבשן האש, Besha'ah shehipil Nimrod harasha es Avraham Avinu l'soch kivshan
haeish, tie in to our period we are in the תורה, when
נמרוד Nimrod threw אברהם into the fiery furnace, אמר גבריאל לפני הקדוש
ברוך הוא, amar Gavriel lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, ריבונו של עולם, Ribbono
shel olam, ארד ואצנן, eired v'atzanein, let me go down and cool
off the fire, ואציל את הצדיק מכבשן האש, v'atzil es hatzaddik mikivshan
haeish, and let me save the righteous person. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך
הוא, Amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu, אני יחיד בעולמי, ani yachid be'olami,
I am singular in my world, והוא יחיד בעולמו, v'hu yachid be'olamo,
he's the only one in the world that believes in God. We
have a very unique relationship, me and אברהם. נאה ליחיד להציל את
היחיד, Na'eh l'yachid lehatzil es hayachid, the singular should save the singular.
ולפי שהקדוש ברוך הוא אינו מקפח שכר כל בריה, Velifi shehakadosh baruch
hu eino mikape'ach sechar kol biryah, God does not hold back the
reward any creature deserves, אמר תזכה ותציל שלושה מבני בניו. tizkeh vesatzil
sheloshah mibnei banav. You will merit to save three, not one, three,
but because it's not unique and individual, three of his descendants. והן
חנניה מישאל ועזריה. V'hen Chananya Mishael v'Azarya. דרש בר שמעון השילוני Darsha
bar Shimon haShiloni בשעה שהפיל נבוכדנצר הרשע את חנניה מישאל ועזריה לכבשן
האש, besha'ah shehipil Nevuchadnezzar harasha es Chananya Mishael v'Azarya l'soch kivshan haeish,
when נבוכדנצר Nebuchadnezzar threw חנניה מישאל ועזריה, Chananya Mishael v'Azarya, אמר יורקמו
שר הברד, amar Yurkamo sar habarad, יורקמו Yurkamo was the name of
the angel over the frost, לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא lifnei Hakadosh Baruch
Hu in front of God, אמר לפניו, amar lefanav, ריבונו של עולם,
Ribbono shel olam, ארד ואצנן את הכבשן, eired v'atzanein es hakivshan, let
me go down and cool off the furnace, ואציל לצדיקים הללו, v'atzil
l'tzaddikim hellu, and let me save those righteous people, מכבשן האש. mikivshan
haeish. אמר לו גבריאל, Amar lo Gavriel, so גבריאל Gavriel came and
said ahem, אין גבורתו של הקדוש ברוך הוא בכך, ein gevuraso shel
Hakadosh Baruch Hu bekach, remember he said God's glory, greatness will not
be shown in that. אתה שר ברד, Atah sar barad, you're frost.
Big deal that the frost can cool off the fire. אלא אני
שר של אש, Ela ani sar shel esh, I'm fire, ארד ואקריר
מבפנים, Eired v'akrir mibifnim, here's what I'm going to do. I'll go
in there, I'll cool it off on the inside ואקדיח מבחוץ v'akdiach
mibachutz and I'll make it hot on the outside so everybody around
will burn, which is what the story says, and everybody on the
inside of the fire will be saved. ונעשה נס בתוך נס, v'na'aseh
nes betoch nes, a miracle within a miracle. I will cool them
off on the inside and heat it up on the outside. It's
like they say by a thermos, right? The amazing thing about a
thermos is it keeps cold things cold and hot things hot, but
how does it know? By the way, okay. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך
הוא, Amar lo haKadosh Baruch Hu, so God said to him, wait,
okay, you go down. באותה שעה פתח גבריאל ואמר B'otah sha'ah patach
Gavriel v'amar ואמת ה׳ לעולם. v'emet Hashem l'olam. Ah, God fulfills His
promises because God told me I get a chance to save the
descendants of Avraham and here was my chance. All right, more tomorrow.
Isn't it unusual to have the statement and then the attestation, such
and such and such, אמר גבריאל? amar Gavriel?